<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Software Engineering | Manuel Pagliuca</title><link>https://manuelpagliuca.github.io/tag/software-engineering/</link><atom:link href="https://manuelpagliuca.github.io/tag/software-engineering/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Software Engineering</description><generator>HugoBlox Kit (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 Dec 2023 14:17:20 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://manuelpagliuca.github.io/media/icon_hu_7cf09ba6a715517.png</url><title>Software Engineering</title><link>https://manuelpagliuca.github.io/tag/software-engineering/</link></image><item><title>Design Patterns in C++</title><link>https://manuelpagliuca.github.io/project/design-patterns/</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 Dec 2023 14:17:20 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://manuelpagliuca.github.io/project/design-patterns/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Personal project, December 2023&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Between the months of November and December I wanted to dig deeper on software engineering, so I decided to study and implement some design patterns. In particular the fundamental one from the &lt;em&gt;Gang of Four&lt;/em&gt; (GoF).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I created a
that acts as a collection of C++ implementations of these patterns. The GoF patterns are all presents but in the future I&amp;rsquo;m planning to add also the &amp;ldquo;extra&amp;rdquo; patterns (at the moment only the &lt;em&gt;null object&lt;/em&gt; is present).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="creational"&gt;Creational&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Design Pattern&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Abstract Factory&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Provides an interface for creating families of related or dependent objects without specifying their concrete classes.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Builder&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Separates the construction of a complex object from its representation, allowing the same construction process to create different representations.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Factory Method&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Defines an interface for creating an object but leaves the choice of its type to the subclasses.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Prototype&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Creates new objects by copying an existing object, known as the prototype.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Singleton&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ensures a class has only one instance and provides a global point of access to that instance.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2 id="structural"&gt;Structural&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Design Pattern&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Adapter&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Allows classes with incompatible interfaces to work together by wrapping its own interface around that of an already existing class.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Bridge&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Decouples an abstraction from its implementation so that the two can vary independently.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Composite&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Composes zero-or-more similar objects so that they can be manipulated as one object.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Decorator&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dynamically adds/overrides behavior in an existing method of an object.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Facade&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Provides a simplified interface to a large body of code.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Flyweight&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Reduces the cost of creating and manipulating a large number of similar objects.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Proxy&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Provides a placeholder for another object to control access, reduce cost, and reduce complexity.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2 id="behavioral"&gt;Behavioral&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Design Pattern&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chain of Responsibility&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Delegates commands to a chain of processing objects.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Command&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Creates objects that encapsulate actions and parameters.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Interpreter&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Implements a specialized language.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Iterator&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Accesses the elements of an object sequentially without exposing its underlying representation.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Mediator&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Allows loose coupling between classes by being the only class that has detailed knowledge of their methods.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Memento&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Provides the ability to restore an object to its previous state (undo).&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Observer&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Is a publish/subscribe pattern, which allows some observer objects to see an event.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;State&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Allows an object to alter its behavior when its internal state changes.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Strategy&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Allows one of a family of algorithms to be selected on-the-fly at runtime.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Template Method&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Defines the skeleton of an algorithm as an abstract class, allowing its subclasses to provide concrete behavior.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Visitor&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Separates an algorithm from an object structure by moving the hierarchy of methods into one object.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During this exploration I discovered many interesting aspects of software engineering by exploring this field, especially a concept of scope level design patterns. Some design patterns can be applied directly on the repository (code level, so in micro), like the GoF patterns or &lt;em&gt;concurrency patterns&lt;/em&gt; for MT paradigms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other design patterns acts on an higher level of abstraction, and these are called &lt;strong&gt;architectural patterns&lt;/strong&gt;. Some of them are widely known like the MVC (Model-View-Controller) or n-tier, but most of them are new to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the future I would like to write a blog post about them with diagrams and explanations, seems a good idea for studying them in a fun way 😁&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>